{"tossups": [{"question": "A participant in this event carried a piece of wood from the Wright Brothers\u2019 first plane with him. William Safire wrote the \u201cFate has ordained\u201d speech in case this event didn\u2019t go as planned. The command module<em> Columbia</em> was piloted by Michael Collins during this event, which an estimated 600 million people watched live on July 20, 1969. For the point, name this \u201cgiant leap for mankind,\u201d a NASA mission in which Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong became the first men to walk on the moon.", "answer": "<b> Apollo 11</b> (prompt on descriptions of the first moon landing; prompt on Apollo alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this dictator of communist Romania.", "answer": "Nicolae<b> Ceausescu</b> [chow-chess-koo]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man signed the Snyder Act, which provided for the enfranchisement of all Native Americans. His reputation greatly increased after working with Edwin Curtis in handling the Boston Police Strike while serving as the governor of Massachusetts. In his highest post, this man\u2019s secretary of state, Frank Kellogg, signed a pact with Aristide Briand that attempted to outlaw war in the aftermath of World War I. For the point, name this \u201csilent\u201d president who succeeded Warren G. Harding.", "answer": "Calvin<b> Coolidge</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Avici is one of these places situated in Naraka in Buddhism. The Florentine Codex describes Tlalocan, one of these places ruled by Chalchiuhtlicue [chall-wee-tl\u2019ee-koh] and Tlaloc, as a region characterized by water. Hun-Came, the owner of a ball court, rules another one of these places, another of which is called Yomi in Shinto traditions. The Isles of the Blessed comprise one of these, along with the Asphodel Fields and Elysium, in Greek mythology. For the point, name these spiritual places ruled by gods like Osiris and Hades, the home of spirits of the dead.", "answer": "mythical<b> underworld</b>s (accept descriptions of<b> realm</b>s of the<b> dead</b>, including<b> hell</b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "It was formed from the union of Sarawak, North Borneo, and a namesake peninsula. In 1965, Singapore was kicked out of, for the point, what Southeast Asian nation whose Petronas Towers are in Kuala Lumpur?", "answer": "<b> Malaysia</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This battle was prompted by Pope Pius V\u2019s pleas to rescue Famagusta. Sebastiano Venier, a future Doge of Venice, rose to prominence after serving in the centre division of this battle alongside the flagship <em>Real</em>, a galley. The author of<em> Don Quixote</em>, Miguel de Cervantes, was wounded in this battle while fighting against the forces of Ali Pasha. For the point, name this 1571 battle in which Don Juan of Austria led the Holy League to victory over the Ottoman fleet.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Lepanto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "William Thornton designed this building, whose interior includes Constantino Brumidi\u2019s <em>The Apotheosis of Washington</em> in a large Rotunda. For the point, name this U.S. government building that houses both the Senate and the House.", "answer": "U.S.<b> Capitol</b> building", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "This man allegedly used the skins of the vanquished generals Atoc and Hango as drums. This man provoked an attack by throwing a Bible to the ground in the presence of the friar Vincente de Valverde. He rose to power after winning the Battle of Quipaipan in the War of the Two Brothers against Huascar. This man was captured and ransomed for a room full of gold after Spanish conquistadors defeated him at Cajamarca. Francisco Pizzaro overthrew, for the point, what last Incan emperor?", "answer": "<b> Atahualpa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "One side in this conflict received funding from France after the Treaty of Barwalde. Despite having won at this war\u2019s battles of Dessau Bridge and Wolgast, Albrecht von Wallenstein was accused of treason and assassinated. One year after Count Tilly was routed at Breitenfeld in this war, an ill-fated cavalry charge at Lutzen led to the death of Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden. The Treaty of Westphalia ended, for the point, what religious war in Europe that lasted from 1618 to 1648?", "answer": "<b> Thirty Years\u2019</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This company\u2019s German subsidiary, Adam Opel AG, was accused of profiting from both sides during World War II. In 1953, Charles Erwin Wilson, this company\u2019s president, was named as Secretary of Defense; during the confirmation hearings, Wilson famously claimed that \u201cwhat\u2019s good for (this company) is good for the country.\u201d This company first surpassed Ford Motor Company in sales in the late 1920s. For the point, name this automobile company whose brands include Buick and Chevrolet.", "answer": "<b> G</b>eneral<b> M</b>otors Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Those who wronged this man were protected by the Amnesty Bill of Waldeck-Rosseau. This man was implicated after a letter was found in ambassador Max von Schwartzkoppen\u2019s garbage. Georges Picquart was sent to North Africa for supporting this man. The crimes of Ferdinand Esterhazy were blamed on this man, who was imprisoned on Devil\u2019s Island. Emile Zola penned the open letter<em> J\u2019accuse</em> in defense of, for the point, what Jewish army officer who was accused of treason in 19th century France, triggering a namesake affair?", "answer": "Alfred<b> Dreyfus</b> (accept<b> Dreyfus</b> Affair)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A national cemetery is located in this island\u2019s Punchbowl Crater. The Admiral Clarey Bridge was built in a harbor of this island, providing easy connection to Ford Island. Diamond Head overlooks this island\u2019s largest city. This island is home to a memorial built over the sunken hull of the USS<em> Arizona</em>, which was lost during a surprise attack on December 7, 1941. For the point, name this most populous Hawaiian island, home to Pearl Harbor and Honolulu.", "answer": "<b> Oahu</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The spy Sicinnus enticed the evenutal losers of this battle to press the attack, despite Artemisia\u2019s preference to fight on land. The losing commander at this battle observed his forces from a throne on Mount Aigaleo. The winning side of this battle had moved ships to the Saronic Gulf after learning of Sparta\u2019s defeat at Thermopylae, leaving Athens undefended. For the point, name this 480 BC naval battle, a victory for Themistocles and the Greeks over Xerxes I, a turning point of the Persian Wars.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Salamis</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This author appeared before HUAC in 1947 to describe the differences between the Soviet Union and its portrayal in the 1944 film<em> Song of Russia</em>. Robert Nozick argued that this thinker failed to address the is-ought problem in an essay published in \u201cThe Personalist.\u201d This philosopher\u2019s support for capitalism, rational egoism, and reason is outlined in her system of Objectivism, as described by John Galt. For the point, name this philosopher and author of<em> Atlas Shrugged</em> and<em> The Fountainhead</em>.", "answer": "Ayn<b> Rand</b> Page 4", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This man ordered troops to besiege Sidi Ifni after a series of rebellions broke out in the Forgotten War. Though his country was officially neutral in World War II, he dispatched the Blue Division to fight against the Soviet Union. The reputation of this man grew after serving as head of the Foreign Legion in the Rif War. This man merged the Carlist and Falange parties and requested the German Condor Legion\u2019s bombing of Guernica in his country\u2019s civil war. For the point, name this Spanish fascist dictator.", "answer": "Francisco<b> Franco</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A military engineer from this country served under Nathanael Greene at the Battle of Guilford Court House. Another military figure from this country died leading the siege of Savannah, is called the \u201cfather of the American cavalry,\u201d and is honored with a holiday in early March in Chicago. Those two commanders from this country aided the American Revolution after gaining experience fighting against Russia. For the point, name this European country where Tadeusz Kosciuezko [tah-dah-oosh koh-shoo-skow] and Casimir Pulaski fought against partitions.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was rebuilt with a pavilion called the Drum Tower at its center. A group based in this city won the War of the Two Capitals when it was known as Khanbaliq. The Summer Palace was built in this city by the Jin Dynasty. This city became the northern terminus of the Grand Canal in the 7th century. The Yongle Emperor moved his capital here, and his son failed to move the capital back to Nanjing. The site of the Forbidden Palace is, for the point, what modern capital of China?", "answer": "<b> Beijing</b> (or<b> Peking</b>; accept<b> Dadu</b>; accept<b> Khanbaliq</b> before mentioned) Page 5", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this president\u2019s tenure, the capture of a ship carrying munitions for Cuban revolutionaries led to the Virginius Affair, though the tension was defused by Secretary of State Hamilton Fish. The Transcontinental Railroad was completed during the tenure of this president, whose private secretary, Orville Babcock, was caught embezzling distillery taxes in Whiskey Ring scandal. The Credit Mobilier scandal hurt the credibility of, for the point, what president and former Union general during the Civil War?", "answer": "Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This kingdom fought a war with its northern neighbor after the murder of its princess Berenice. The founder of this kingdom lost control of Cyprus after a defeat to Antigonid Macedonia. It defeated its rival, the Seleucid Empire, at the Battle of Raphia for control of Syria. Its last ruler went on a luxury cruise with Julius Caesar and committed suicide after the death of her lover, Mark Antony. For the point, name this Diadochi kingdom ruled by the Ptolemaic dynasty, which ended with the death of Cleopatra.", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b> (accept the<b> Ptolemaic</b> Kingdom until mentioned) Page 6", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}